A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980 FA739G
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Improving access to financial services: strategies for influencing the private marketplace, 2011 presentation (Reports 019494), Brown, Amy L.
  Economic Opportunity and Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS);Financial Assets
  Low-income consumers; Poor; Finance, Personal; Households -- Economic aspects
- Climate change, forests peoples, and justice - recent developments, 2011 presentation (Reports 019495), Kaimowitz, David; Riggs, Peter J.
  Economic Opportunity and Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS)/Sustainable development
  Developing countries -- Economic conditions; Natural resource management -- Developing countries; Conservation of natural resources -- Brazil; Indigenous peoples -- Civil rights; Land tenure -- Brazil; Land tenure -- Indonesia; Community forests -- Developing countries; Reducing Emissions from Deforestation and Forest Degradation (Program)
- Kenya: engaging land reforms in a renewed policy environment, 2011 presentation (Reports 019496), Rugadya, Margaret
  Natural resource management -- Kenya; Land tenure -- Kenya; Land reform -- Kenya; Land tenure -- Women; Women in agriculture -- Kenya; Women and land use planning
- Higher education and racial justice in Brazil, 2011 presentation (Reports 019497), Toni, Ana; Dora, Denise Dourado
  Democracy, Rights, and Governance
  Indigenous peoples -- Civil rights; Indigenous peoples -- Education, Higher -- Brazil; Land tenure -- Brazil; Ford Foundation. Rights and Governance
- Educational opportunity and scholarship: building knowledge for social justice, 2011 presentation (Reports 019498), Oakes, Jeannie
  Education, Higher; Social justice; Equality -- Economic aspects; Income distribution -- United States
- Creating a fair and equitable criminal justice system, 2010 presentation (Reports 019499), Levingston, Kirsten D.
  Criminal justice, Administration of
- Urban poverty exploration presentation (Reports 019500), 2010; McKeon, Elizabeth, 1962-
  Poverty; City planning; Urban poor -- Housing; Slums -- Developing countries; Urban planning and research; Ford Foundation. Transparent, effective and accountable government (TEAG)
- American Society of International Law: Panel on U.S. law schools and developing countries (Reports 019501), 1968; Edwards, Robert H. (Robert Hazard), 1935- (Box 894)
  A report on the role of U.S. legal education and overseas legal cooperation. Several of the case studies in this report were Ford Foundation grantees.
  21 p.
  AME Staff Files
  Law -- Study and teaching -- Developing countries
- American Society of International Law: Panel on U.S. law schools and developing countries (Reports 019502), 1967; Edwards, Robert H. (Robert Hazard), 1935- (Box 894)
  "In this exploratory session the Panel ranged generally over aspects of legal underdevelopment and on the American Response ... which includes recommendationson research, training, and legal cooperation relating to developing countries." [p. 1-2] Two of t
- Summary comments on capacity-building in educational planning and research (Reports 019503), 1975; Bell, David E., 1919-2000; Drysdale, Robert S.; Scott, Thomas D.; Harrington, Fred Harvey, 1912-; Meeting on Assistance to Education (1975) (Box 894)
  Comments by Messrs. Bell, Drysdale, Scott and Harrington at the recent meeting on Assistance to Education held September 16 through 18 in 1975. Two attachments - Mr. Silvert's statement and Mr. Ward's comments mentioned in the introductory memo are missin
  Education and Research
  1, 5, 5, 4, 4 p.
  AME staff files
  Education -- Research
- Notes on building capacity for educational research (Reports 019504), 1975; Myers, Robert G. (Box 894)
  Education -- Research -- Technical assistance
- International Division Conference: Rapporteurs' reports (Reports 019505), 1975; International Division Conference (1975, September 29-23) (Box 894)
  Rappportuers' reports from the Ford Foundation International Division conference held from September 19 to 23, 1975.
  121 p.
  International Division Conference (1975, September 29-23)
- Visit to Geneva, September 3-6 (Reports 019506), 1975; Ward, F. Champion (Box 894)
- International Division Conference: agenda papers for session III-3 (Reports 019507), 1975; International Division Conference (1975, September 19-23) (Box 894)
  Background papers on the objectives of the Resources and Environment office in its international activities and a retrospective on Ford's past activities in the field. The panel session on Resources and the environment was held on Saturday 20, 1975.
  2, 8, 9 p.
  International Division Conference (1975, September 19-23)
- International Division Conference: agenda papers for session IV-2 (Reports 019508), 1975; International Division Conference (1975, September 19-23) (Box 894)
  Background papers for the session on public management.
  14, 4, 5 p.
- International Division Conference: agenda paper for session IV-1 (Reports 019509), 1975; International Division Conference (1975, September 19-23) (Box 894)
  The agenda paper was prepared by Lyle Saunders as background for the panel discussion on population development held on Setpmeber 22, 1975. The paper is titled Population: pre- and post-Bucharest.
  12 p.
- Ford Foundation and public management in the less-developed countries: agenda paper for session IV-2 (Reports 019510), 1975; Sutton, Francis X. (Francis Xavier); Smith, Theodore M.; International Division Conference (1975, September 19-23) (Box 894)
  Background paper for the session on public management held on September 22, 1975.
  77 p.
- ASIL Committee on U.S. law schoools and developing countries: discussion paper (Reports 019511), 1966 (Box 894)
  Discussion paper for December 2-3, 1966 meeting.
  Africa and the Middle East
  Law -- Study and teaching
- Report on legal education in Nicaragua (Reports 019512), 1968; Helfeld, David M. (Box 894)
  32 p.
  Law -- Study and teaching -- Nicaragua
- Panel on law and developing countries (Reports 019513), 1967; Sweeney, Joseph M. (Box 894)
  A review of the New York University program in Ankara to provide assistance to the University of Ankara in the fields of business administration, education and law.
  14 p.
  Education, Higher -- Technical assistance; Teachers -- Training of -- Ankara (Turkey)
- The need for new approaches to legal education in Africa: some observations and proposals (Reports 019514), 1968 (Box 894)
  9 p. + appendix
  Law -- Study and teaching; Lawyers -- Africa
- Report on the media in South Africa (Reports 019515), 1992; Matisonn, John (Box 894)
  Mass media -- South Africa; Press; Newspapers; Radio broadcasting; Television broadcasting
- The media landscape of South Africa draft (Reports 019516), 1992; Powell, Adam C., 1946- (Box 894)
- Report on a visit to South Africa, Mozambique and Zimbabwe (Reports 019517), 1992; Fergusson, Frances D. (Frances Daly); Moohr, Michael (Box 894)
  Frances D. Fergusson was a Ford Foundation Trustee from 1989 to 2001. Michael Moohr was a consultant for Ford Foundation who evaluated initiatives in Africa, India and China.
  54 p.
  Education -- South Africa
- The Latin America regional initiative in higher education: a strategy paper (Reports 019518), 1991 (Box 894)
  Overview of Ford Foundation's grantmaking in higher education in Latin America and goals and strategies for a regional initiative on higher education.
  Education and Culture
  Education, Higher -- Latin America
- A consultative process to revitalize African higher education: discussion paper (Reports 019519), 1990 (Box 894)
  10 p.
  Education, Higher -- Africa; Educational equalization; Educational change -- Africa
- Sixth meeting of the African Commission on Human and People's Rights (Reports 019520), 1990; Hodges, Tony (Box 894)
  Tony Hodges explores the idea of establishing a trust fund for the Commission to enable it to continue its work. See also Reports 019521.
  Human rights -- Africa; African Commission on Human and People's Rights
- African Commission on Human and People's Rights (Reports 019521), 1990; Morris, Diana (Box 894)
  Report on the merits and logistics of a trust fund for the Commission, the role of the Gambian Human Rights Center and the progress of the Commission to date. See also Reports 019520.
- Report of the working group meeting on the books sector for Sub-Saharan Africa (Reports 019522), 1989 (Box 894)
  John Gerhart represented the Ford Foundation at this meeting. Ford Foundation provides support for the books sector through university libraries, general publishing including university presses, indigenous authors and the African Books Collective, and exc
  Publishers and publishing -- Africa; Authors -- Africa; Scholarly journal publishing -- Africa
- Building broader women's health/reproductive healthcare coalitions in the states: a look at Idaho, Taxes and Florida: An Open Society Institute Initiative (Reports 019523), 2000; McGovern, Theresa M. (Box 894)
  This report analyzes women's health advocacy efforts in three states: Texas, Florida and Idaho, and provides recommendations on specific funding interventions to address documented obstacles to achieving significant gains in women's reproductive and over
  103 p.
  Office files of Melvin L. Oliver
  Reproductive health -- Texas; Reproductive health -- Idaho; Reproductive health -- Florida; Women's health services; Patient advocacy
- A scan of the Assets Program's Affinity Groups (Reports 019524), 1999; Plastrik, Peter (Box 894)
  An overview of the ASSET Program's three affinity groups, their progress, concerns and needs.
  16 p.
- Institutions and uncertainty: new directions in natural resource management Draft (Reports 019525), 1999; Way, Sally-Anne (Box 894)
  This document is a summary of IDS Discussion paper 372 (November 1999), Exploring understandings of institutions and uncertainty: new directions in natural resource management. The paper was produced with funding provided by the Ford Foundation.
  Natural resources -- Management; Rural poor
- The state of community based forest management in the Philippines and the role of local governments (Reports 019526), 1999; La Vina, Antonio G. M. (Box 894)
  This paper looks at the state of community based forest management (CBFM) in the Philippines in the context of the role of local governments in implementing this forest management strategy adopted by the Philippine government.
  20 p,
  Forest management; Rural poor; Community-based conservation -- Philippines; Conservation of natural resources -- Philippines
- Update on the development finance industry - where are the gaps that the GI/IF might fill? a report for the Ford Foundation - AGDF (Reports 019527), 2002 (Box 894)
  In 2001, the consultant was engaged by the Ford Foundation to assist the Affinity Group for Development Finance in defining next steps for the Global Institute / Investment Fund initiative that has been under consideration by the group.
  76 p.,: ill., tables, charts
  Development Credit corporations; Poor -- Services for; Microfinance
- Development finance: a background paper on the state of the field (Reports 019528), 2001; Faulhaber, Ingrid (Box 894)
  The paper was prepared for the Affinity Group of Development Finance as part of an initiative to develop a Visiting Scholar Program for the Ford Foundation's work in the field of Development Finance and Economic Security.
- the Ford Foundation's global role in advancing development finance and economic security, 2001, Thomas F. Miller (Reports 019529), Miller, Thomas F. (Box 894)
  The purpose of this paper is to present findings and recommendations from a review of how the Foundation might become more strategic and expand its global role in furthering the field of Development Finance and Economic Security. (p. 1)
- Africa Philanthropy Initiative (API): first year progress report (Reports 019530), 1999 (Box 894)
  The African Philanthropy Initiative's purposes are to support the development of indigenous foundations in Africa and add to the Foundation's world-wide knowledge of foundation building and the role of such institutions in civil society.
  Africa Philanthropy Initiative
  Poor -- Services for -- Africa; Non-governmental organizations -- Africa
- On-time grantmaking: task force report #2 (Reports 019531), 2002; Petrovich, Janice (Box 894)
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Administration
- Maputo trip report: SIA workshop on peace and conflicts in Africa (Reports 019532), 2002; Aidoo, Akwasi (Box 894)
  Workshops were held with leading figures from across the African continent to identify priorities and opportunities for collaboration among organizations and individuals to promote peace and address conflicts in Africa.
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Africa; Peace-building -- Africa; Special Initiatives for Africa (Ford Foundation)
- Reflections on the Ford Foundation's role in building a global field of development finance and economic security (Reports 019533), 2002; DeGiovanni, Frank F. (Box 894)
  Reflections on the work of the Affinity Group on Development Finance and proposals for developing a global strategy on development finance.
  Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS)/Development Finance and Economic Security
  15 p.
  Development Credit corporations; Microfinance; Poor -- Services for; Ford Foundation. Affinity Group on Development Finance
- To run is not to arrive: what hope for transboundary natural resources management in Southern Africa? (Reports 019534), 2001; Katerere, Y.; Mohamed-Katerere, Jennifer Clare (Box 895)
  Paper prepared for the Ford Foundation Environment and Development Affinity Group (EDAG) conference in Cape Town, South Africa held in January 2002.
  Environment and Development Affinity Group Conference (2002: Cape Town, South Africa)
  Land reform; Land use, Rural; Land tenure; Farm tenancy -- Economic aspects; Natural resources; Community-based conservation -- South Africa
- Room for hope: tenure security for farm workers? (Reports 019535), 2001; Centre for Rural Legal Studies (Stellenbosch, South Africa) (Box 895)
  Land reform; Land use, Rural; Land tenure; Farm tenancy -- Economic aspects; Natural resources; Community-based conservation -- South Africa; Agricultural laborers -- South Africa; Centre for Rural Legal Studies (Stellenbosch, South Africa)
- South African national parks: land acquisition strategy, land claims and transfrontier conservation areas (Reports 019536), 2002; Magome, Hector (Box 895)
  Land reform; Land use, Rural; Natural resources; Community-based conservation -- South Africa; National parks and reserves -- South Africa; Natural resources conservation areas
- An overview of land claims in protected areas in South Africa (Reports 019537), 2002; Poonan, Unjinee (Box 895)
  This paper presents an overview of land claims in protected areas in South Africa. A case study of conflict resolution in land claims in protected areas is used to demonstrate the complexities of the process and the policy issues.[]Paper prepared for the Ford Foundation Environment and Development Affinity Group (EDAG) conference in Cape Town, South Africa held in January 2002.
  85 p.
- Gender, environment and sustainable development: reflections from rural voices, N. C. Songelwa (Reports 019538), 2002; Songelwa, N. C. (Box 895)
  Land reform; Land tenure, Rural; Rural women; Natural resources; Community-based conservation -- South Africa
- Land reform processes in South Africa (Reports 019539), 2002; Hlatshwayo, Zakes (Box 895)
  Land reform; Land use, Rural; Natural resources; Community-based conservation -- South Africa
- Namibia country paper: land reform and transition in Namibia (Reports 019540), 2002; Dempers, Im Uhuru (Box 895)
- Land reform and transition in South Africa (Reports 019541), 2002; Greenberg, Stephen (Box 895)
- Land reform and transition in Zimbabwe, draft (Reports 019542), 2002; Moyo, Sam (Box 895)
- Building natural assets and wealth to reduce poverty: concepts and potential applications in the United States (Reports 019543), 2000; Oliver, Melvin L.; Conroy, Michael E.; Coward, E. Walter (Box 895)
  This paper explores the intersection of two conceptual approaches, the "assets" approach to poverty reduction and the concept of "ecological poverty" which emerged from India.
  Rural poor; Natural resources, Communal
- Can the natural assets of cities help address urban poverty? (Reports 019544), 2000; Watson, Greg (Box 895)
  Urban poor -- United States; Urban development; City planning; Land use, Urban; Vacant lands; Brownfields
- Corporate involvement initiative: frameworks and findings from the learning agenda, draft (Reports 019545), 2003 (Box 895)
  The report was prepared for Ford Foundation Grantee Convening, June 2-4, 2003 by Brody, Weiser, Burns.
  CI
  26 p.
  Corporations -- Charitable contributions; Economic security
- Low-cost bank accounts and the EITC: how financial institutions can reach the unbanked and facilitate savings, draft (Reports 019546), 2000; Beverly, Sondra G.; Tescher, Jennifer; Marzahl, David (Box 895)
  This paper presents findings from an on-going evaluation of the Extra Credit Savings Program (ECSP). The first section provides background inofrmation on unbanked families and the EITC, and the second describes the ECSP. The third section describes data s
  52 p.
  Economic security; Low-income consumers; Savings accounts; Extra Credit Savings Program (ECSP)
- Moving toward inclusion: a proposed approach for a discussion of strategy at Commonweal (Reports 019547), 2000 (Box 895)
  Prepared for the Ford Foundation. "The following paper provides background and suggests a framework for the upcoming discussion at Commonweal sponsored by the Ford Foundation. It is hoped that the discussion will assist Ford in crafting a program strategy
  Urban poor -- United States; Urban development
- Scan of opportunities for the Ford Foundation's Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (Reports 019548), 2000; Hamilton, Ralph; Parzen, Julia (Box 895)
  Executive summary of a survey conducted with leaders in the various fields linked with the Susstainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative.
  Urban poor -- United States; Urban development; Sustainable urban development; Ford Foundation. Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative
- The informal solid waste sector in Egypt: prospects for formalization (Reports 019549), 2001; Community and Institutional Development (Box 895)
  Study funded by the Institute of International Education (IIE) and the Ford Foundation.
  65 p.
  Refuse and refuse disposal -- Egypt; Salvage (Waste, etc.); Recycling (Waste, etc.); Community and Institutional Development
- The persistence of poverty in a changing world (Reports 019550), 2001; Oliver, Melvin L.; Grant, David M. (Box 895)
  The authors address definitions and measures of poverty focusing on the difference between absolute and relative measures of poverty. They then move to a discussion of poverty in the U. S. and in the less-developed countries The final section of the chapt
  Poverty; Urban poor -- United States
- Rapportuer's notes on meeting with representatives of U.S. based international organizations to discuss the Reproductive Health and Population Program's external review team report, March 27 (Reports 019551), 1997; Scott, A. O., 1966- (Box 895)
  As part of its ongoing midpoint review of the strategies set forth in 1990 for the Reproductive Health and Population Program, the Foundation invited a number of its partners in the U.S. to help assess events in the field of reproductive health in the cur
  Reproductive Health and Population
  Reproductive health
- Rapportuer's notes on meeting with representatives of U.S. based international organizations to discuss the Reproductive Health and Population Program's external review team report, April 15 (Reports 019552), 1997; Scott, A. O., 1966- (Box 895)
  As part of the Foundation's five-year review of its Reproductive Health and Population Program, a group of domestic grantees was convened on April 15 for a day-long discussion of the current state of the field.
  Reproductive health; Sexual health
- Interim report to the Affinity Group on Development Finance: Development finance institutions, small and medium sized enterprises and low-income impacts, draft (Reports 019553), 1999; Anderson, Richard (Box 895)
  This interim report provides an analysis of the impact that development finance institutions (DFIs) in the United States have had on small and medium sized enterprises (SMEs) and, through SMEs, on low-income populations. (p. 1)
  Developoment credit corporations; Small business
- Affinity Group on Development Finance: 1999 - 2000 operating plan and project status: second draft (Reports 019554) (Box 895)
- Who Owns Us? A discussion paper on key dimensions of ownership and governance in evolving community development finance institutions (Reports 019555), 1999; Duggleby, Tamara J. (Box 895)
  23 p.
  Developoment credit corporations
- Investing in micro-insurance: briefing paper (Reports 019556), 1999; Brown, Warren; Churchill, Craig Farren, 1964- (Box 895)
  Microfinance; Poor -- Services for
- Grantmakers orientation handbook (Reports 019557), 2006 (Box 895)
  Handbook for Ford Foundation grantmaking procedures, office personnel documentation, and affirmative action stance, and provides history of the Foundation, budgets and program summaries.
  157 p. ill: graphs, charts
  Orientation notebook for grantmakers
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Office management; Endowments -- Officials and employees
- Improving access to financial services: the role of policy and regulation, 2011 presentation (Reports 019558), Brown, Amy L.
- Social security reform: challenges and Ford's response presentation (Reports 019559), 2010; Kijakazi, Kilolo, 1956-
  Economic security -- United States; Poor -- United States; Social security
- The Ford Foundation annual report (Reports 019560), 2007
  Contains president's review, program reports, listing of grants, financial statements and lists of staff and trustees.
  Annual Report 2007
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Education; Arts; Community development; Reproductive health; HIV (Viruses); Civil rights; Human rights; Public policy; Social justice; Democracy; Poor; Environmental accountability; International relations
- The Ford Foundation annual report (Reports 019561), 2008
  Annual Report 2008
- The Ford Foundation annual report (Reports 019562), 2009
  Annual Report 2009
- Origins, journeys, returns: Ford Foundation International Fellowships Program (Reports 019563), 2010
  The Ford Foundation International Fellowships Program (IFP) began with the conviction that social justice is advanced through equitable higher education. The program provides fellowships for post-graduate study to emerging leaders from marginalized and ex
  International Fellowship Program
  36 p.: ill.
  Restricted from scholarly access Open in 2021
  People with social disabilities -- Education, Higher -- Developing countries -- Educational equalization; Education, Higher
- Socialist Republic of Vietnam university consolidation project: economic issues for higher education in Vietnam draft (Reports 019564), 1992 (Box 895)
  This report provides a review of the current pattern of higher education finance in Vietnam and how financing can be improved and sustained.
  Asia and the Pacific
  Office files of Peter F. Geithner
  Education (Higher) -- Vietnam
- Report on the visit to Vietnam with Peter F. Geithner (Reports 019565), 1991; Hussain, Athar (Box 895)
  The purpose of the visit was to investigate the possibilities of increasing the number of trained economists and developing policy-oriented research in Vietnam. p. 1.